The American Pronunciation Guide Presents ''How to Pronounce Psychologist''
Sir, I would like to ask you,
as you are such a well-known physicist and scientist,
practically every schoolboy knows about you throughout the world,
I would like to ask,
after all these four or five dialogues that we have had,
what will change man?
What will bring about a radical transformation
in the total consciousness of human being?
Well, I mean,
I don't know that the scientific background
is going to be very relevant to that question.
Would be?
It's not clear that the scientific background
must be relevant to that question.
No, probably not.
But after we have talked considerable at length,
not only now but in the previous years,
what is the energy
– I am using the energy not in any scientific sense,
just ordinary sense –
the vitality, the energy, the drive,
which seems to be lacking?
I mean, after all,
if I listened to you as a viewer,
the three of us,
I would say, yes,
it's all very well for these philosophers
or these scientists,
these experts,
but it's outside my field,
it's too far away.
Bring it nearer.
Bring it much closer, sir,
so that I can deal with my life.
Well, I think at the end of the last discussion
we were touching on one point of that nature
because we were discussing images.
Images, yes.
And the self-image,
and the questioning whether we have to have images at all.
Of course, we went into that.
But you see,
I want, as a viewer,
totally outside,
listening to you for the first time,
the three of you,
I say, look,
how does it touch my life?
Is it so...
it's all so vague and uncertain
and needs a great deal of thinking,
which I am unwilling to do.
Right.
You follow?
So please tell me,
in a few words or at length,
what am I to do with my life?
Where am I to touch it?
Where am I to break it down?
Where am I to...
from where am I to look at it?
I have hardly any time.
I go to the office,
I go to the factory,
I have got so many things to do
– children, wife, nagging, poverty.
You follow?
The whole structure of misery.
And you sit there, you three,
and talk about something which...
sanamatushpa,
that doesn't touch me in the least.
So could we bring it down
to...
brass tacks, as it were,
to where I can grapple with it
as an ordinary human being?
Well, could we consider
the problems arising in daily relationship
as the starting point?
That is the essence, isn't it?
Yes.
I was going to begin with that.
You see, my relationship with human beings
is in the office,
in the factory,
on a golf course...
Or at home.
And at home it is pretty,
you know, a routine –
sex, children,
if I have children, if I want children.
And the constant battle, battle, battle,
all my life,
insulted, wounded, hurt,
everything is going on
in me and around me.
Yes, there is continual disappointment.
Continual disappointment, continual hope,
desire to be more successful,
more money, more, more, more, more
of everything.
Now, where is my...
how am I to alter, change,
my relationship?
What is the raison d'être,
the source of my relationship?
If we could tackle that a little bit
this morning, a little bit,
and go on to what we were discussing,
really, which was much...
which is really very important,
which is not to have an image at all.
Yes.
But I mean, it seems that,
as we were discussing yesterday,
we tend to be related
to the relationship
almost always through the image,
in other words.
Through the image, that's right.
Say, I have an image of myself and of you
as you should be in relation to me.
Yes.
And then that gets disappointed and hurt,
and so on.
But how am I to change that image?
How am I to break it down?
I know after you have talked to me
as an ordinary human being,
I see very well I have got an image,
and it has been put...
put together, constructed through generations.
And I have got it.
I am fairly intelligent,
I am fairly aware of myself,
and I see I have got it.
How am I to break it down?
Well, the point, as I see it,
is that I have got to be aware of that image,
to watch it as it moves, you see.
So, am I to watch it?
Yes.
I am thinking the opposite.
Am I to watch it in the office?
Yes.
In the factory, at home, on the golf club?
Because all those, in all these areas,
are my relationships.
Yes.
I would say I have to watch it on all those places,
and also when I am not there.
When I am not there.
So, I have to watch it all the time, in fact.
Yes.
Now, am I capable of it?
I have got the energy,
because my wife wants sex,
I don't want sex, or I enjoy sex,
I go through all kinds of miseries,
and at the end of the day, I have hardly...
I crawl into bed.
And you say, I must have energy.
Yes.
So, I must realize
relationship is the greatest importance.
Yes.
Therefore, I am willing to give up certain
wastage of energies.
Which wastage?
What kind of wastage?
Drink.
Drink, yes.
Smoke.
Useless chatter.
Yes.
Endless crawling from pub to pub.
That would be the beginning, anyway.
That would be the beginning.
But I am...
You see, I want all those, plus more.
You follow?
But if I can see that everything depends on this...
Of course.
Then I won't go to the pub, you see,
if I see that that interferes.
So, I must, as an ordinary human being,
I must realize the greatest importance
is to have right relationship.
Yes.
But I mean that if I don't...
It would be good if we could say what happens
when we don't have it, you see, that we...
Oh, when I don't have it, of course.
Then everything goes to pieces.
Everything goes to pieces.
Not only everything goes to pieces,
but everything goes to pieces.
I create such havoc around me.
So, can I, by putting aside smoke, drink, pubs,
and, you know, the endless chatter about this or that,
will I gather that energy?
Well, that's the beginning.
That's what I'm asking.
Will I gather that energy,
which will help me
to face the picture which I have,
the image which I have?
Yes, it means growing also ambition
and many other things.
Of course.
You see, I begin by obvious things
like smoke, drink, pub,
all the rest of the chatter.
Let me just stop you here.
Suppose my image is that
you're going to do it for me,
and my real image is
that I can't do it for myself.
Oh, that's one of our favorite conditioning,
that I can't do it myself,
therefore I must go to somebody to help me.
Or I go to the pub
because I see I can't do it for myself,
so I create the condition.
Several things come from my going to the pub.
One is I'm in despair
because I can't do it for myself,
so I'm going to obliterate myself through drink.
So I no longer feel this pain.
At least for the moment.
That's right.
And also, too, I'm proving to myself
that my image that I can't do it for myself is right.
After all, look at me,
I'm on the ground in the gutter.
You're going to deny that?
Second of all,
by treating myself in such a way,
I'm going to prove to you I can't do it myself,
and maybe I'll get you to do it for me.
No, I think, sir,
I think we don't realize
any of us the utter
and absolute importance
of right relationship.
I don't think we realize it.
I agree with you, we don't.
With my wife, with my neighbor,
with the office, wherever I am,
I don't think we realize,
with nature also,
a relationship which is easy,
quiet, full, rich, happy,
you know, the beauty of it,
the harmony of it.
We don't realize that.
Now, can we tell the ordinary viewer,
the listener,
the great importance of that?
Let's try.
How can we communicate to somebody
the value of a right relationship?
You're my wife,
you're whining,
you're nagging me, right?
You think that I should do it
or that I should be doing something
from you when I'm tired
and I don't feel like doing anything for you.
I know.
Right?
Go to a party.
That's right.
Let's go to the party, right?
You should...
You never take me out.
Yes.
Right?
You never take me anywhere.
Yes.
So how are we...
How are you...
How are you who realize
the importance of relationship
to deal with me?
How are you to deal?
No, I mean,
we've got this problem in life.
Yes, I mean,
I think it should be very clear
that nobody can do it for me.
You see that whatever somebody else does,
it won't affect my relationship.
How are you going to make that clear?
But isn't it obvious?
I mean, I should say it.
It's not obvious.
I feel very strongly,
I'm the viewer,
I feel very strongly
that you ought to be doing it for me.
But how can I...
My mother never did it for me.
Somebody's got to do it for me.
But I mean,
it's not obvious that it can't be done.
I mean, I'm saying that
that's just a delusion
because whatever you do,
I will be in the same relationship
as before.
I mean, suppose you live a perfect life.
I mean, I can't imitate it,
so, you know,
I'll just go on as before, won't I?
Right.
So I have to do something myself.
Isn't that clear?
But I don't feel able
to do anything myself.
But then can you see that
if you don't do anything yourself...
Then you're lost.
It's inevitable.
I mean, any idea that it will ever get better
is a delusion.
Well, do you want to say then,
or can we say that right relationship
begins with the realization
that I have to do something for myself?
And the utter importance of it.
Right.
The utter importance,
the responsibility I have for myself.
Because you are the world.
Right.
And the world is you.
You can't shirk that.
Well, perhaps we could discuss that a bit
because it may seem strange
to the viewer.
To some of the viewer,
to say I am the world.
But you are, after all that you are thinking,
all your, you are the result of the culture,
the climate, the food, the environment,
the economic conditions,
you are the result of all that.
Well, you can see that.
I mean, I think you can see that.
That's right, yes.
That's what you mean.
I mean, I just want to say
that's what you mean by saying
you are the world.
Well, I think you can see that
in just what I've just been laying out here
about the person who feels
that he's entitled to be taken care of
by the world.
The world is in fact
moving in that direction
of all the pleasure
and the technological...
No, sir, this is a simple fact.
You go to India,
you see the same suffering,
same anxieties,
and you come to Europe, America,
it's in essence, it is the same.
Though each person has
the same basic structure
of suffering and confusion
and deception and so on.
And therefore if I say I am the world,
I mean that there's a universal structure
and it's part of me
and I'm part of it.
I'm part of that.
Quite.
So, now, let's proceed from there.
Right.
The first thing you have to tell me
as an ordinary human being
living in this mad rat race,
you have to tell me,
look, realise the utter greatest
important things in life is relationship.
You cannot have relationship
if you have an image about yourself.
Or if you create a pleasurable image
and stick to that.
Or the image that you're entitled to,
so that it comes before...
Any form of image
you have about another
or about yourself
prevents the beauty of relationship.
Right.
Yes, say the image that I'm secure
in such and such a situation, for example.
Right. Yes.
And not secure in a different situation.
That prevents relationship.
That's right.
Because I will say I demanded the other person
that he put me in the situation
that I think is secure, you see.
Right.
And then he may not want that.
So that my relationship,
if I have the image
of the pleasurable relationship,
then all my actions
are with reference to this other person
that I try to force him...
To give me...
...to move me into doing that
so that I have, A, I say to him,
you should be this way,
because that would complete my image.
Two, I have what I call claims on the other person.
In other words, I expect him
to act in such a way that he acknowledges that image.
Yes, or I may say I have the image
of what is just and right and so on.
So in other words,
it's not that it's personally so,
but I say that would be the right way
for everybody to behave.
Right, in order to complete my image.
Yes. So, for example, I would say that,
say the wife says, you know,
husbands ought to take their wives out
to parties frequently.
Right.
That's part of the image.
Or husbands have corresponding images.
Right, right.
And therefore,
and then that image gets hurt, do you see?
Right.
Now, but I think we have to be very specific
about that each little piece of this
is with fury...
With energy.
...and energy and fury, necessity
to complete this image and relationship.
Therefore, relationship
gets forced into a model.
Yes, sir, I understand all that.
But you see, most of us are not serious.
We want an easy life.
You come along and tell me,
look, relationship is the greatest thing.
I say, quite right, and I carry on the old way.
What I'm trying to get at is,
what will make a relationship
a human being listen to this,
even seriously, for two minutes?
They won't listen to you.
Right.
If you went to one of the big experts
on psychology or whatever it is,
they won't take time to listen to you.
They've got their plans, their pictures,
their images, you follow?
They're surrounded by all this.
So to whom are we talking to?
Well, to whoever can listen.
We're talking to ourselves.
Not only that.
To whom are we talking to?
Well, whoever is able to listen.
That means somebody who is somewhat serious.
Yes.
And I think, you see,
that we even may form an image of ourselves
as not capable of being serious and so on.
That's right.
In other words, that it's too hard.
Too hard, yes.
That's an image to say that I want it easy,
which means it comes from the image
this is beyond my capacity.
Quite.
So let's move from there.
Right.
We say as long as you have an image,
pleasant or unpleasant,
created, etc., etc.,
put together by thought and so on,
there is no right relationship.
That's an obvious fact.
Right.
Yes, and life ceases to have any value
without right relationship.
Yes.
Life ceases to have any value
without right relationship.
Now my consciousness is filled with these images.
Right.
Is it?
Mm-hm.
Right?
And the images make my consciousness.
That's right.
Now you are asking me,
to have no images at all.
That means no consciousness as I know it now.
Right, sir?
Yes.
Well, could we say anyway that the major part
of consciousness is the self-image?
Is that what you are saying?
Yes.
There may be some other parts, but...
We'll come to that.
We'll come to that later.
But the most of it for now is...
Yes.
We are mostly occupied with the self-image.
That's right.
Mm-hm.
What about the self-image
and the whole way it generates itself?
What do you think?
Well, I think we discussed that before,
that it gets caught on thinking of the self as real.
Mm-hm.
And it's always implicit to say,
you know, for example,
the image may be that I am suffering
in a certain way,
and you see,
or I must get rid of the suffering.
But you see, there's always the implicit meaning in that,
that I am there real,
and therefore I must keep on thinking about this reality.
Right.
And it gets caught in that feedback
we were talking about,
that the thought feeds back...
Mm-hm.
...and builds up.
It builds up more images.
More images, yes.
More images.
And so that's the consciousness.
I mean, content of my consciousness...
Consciousness is all images.
...is vast series of images.
Right.
Interrelated, not separate, interrelated.
Mm-hm.
But they're all centred on the self, isn't it?
Of course. The self is the centre.
Yes, because they're all aimed at...
they're all for the self...
Yes.
...in order to make the self right, you know, correct.
And the self is regarded as all-important.
Yes.
That gives it tremendous energy.
Now, what I'm getting at is,
you're asking me,
who am fairly serious, fairly intelligent,
as an ordinary human being,
you're asking me to empty that consciousness.
Right.
I'm asking you to stop this image-making.
Not only the image-making.
The images that I have...
Mm-hm.
...and prevent further image-making.
Right, right.
Both are involved.
Yes, yes.
I'm asking you to look at the machinery of consciousness.
Yes.
Wait a minute.
I want to get at that.
This is very important because...
Okay, let's go.
You're asking me,
and I want to understand you...
Mm-hm.
...because I want to do...
I really want to live a different way of living,
because I see it is necessary.
I don't play with words.
Right.
I am not...
I don't want to be high-floating.
I want to deal with this thing.
Okay.
You're asking me to be free of the self,
which is the maker of images,
Mm-hm.
and to prevent further image-making.
Right.
And I say, please tell me what to do,
how to do it.
Mm-hm.
And you tell me,
the moment when you ask me how to do it,
you're already building an image.
Yes.
The system, the method.
Yes, I mean, one could say that...
when you say, how am I to do it,
so you have already put I in the middle...
In the middle.
...the same image as before
with a slightly different content.
So, you tell me,
don't ever ask how to do it,
because the how involves the me doing it.
Right, right.
Therefore I am creating another picture.
Right.
So that shows the way the thing...
you slip into it,
because you say how to do it,
the word me is not there,
but it's there implicitly.
Implicit, yes.
And therefore you slip in because...
How am I to do it?
Of course.
Yes, but it's the way...
it usually slips in because it's there implicitly,
not explicitly.
Yes, implicitly.
That's often the trick.
I mean...
Explicit, yes.
Right, right.
Now, so you stop me,
and you say, then proceed from there.
How am I to free this consciousness,
even a corner of it,
a limited part of it,
is there...
what is the action that will do it?
I want to discuss it with you.
Don't tell me how to do it.
I've understood you.
Yes, yes.
I've understood.
I will never again ask how to do it.
The how, as he explained, implies implicit...
Implicit, yes.
Implicit in the me,
the me wanting to do it,
and therefore the me is the factor of the image-maker.
Right.
Right, I've understood that very clearly.
Then I said to you,
I realise this,
what am I to do?
Do you realise it?
Yes, I know it.
I know I am making images all the time.
I'm very well aware.
Yes, but at what point?
Wait, let me finish.
I'm very well aware of it.
My wife calls me an idiot.
Right.
Already registered in the brain.
Thought takes it over.
It becomes the image which I have about myself is hurt.
Yes.
Right?
So this process I know,
I'm very well aware of this.
Right.
Because I've discussed with you,
I've gone into it.
I see, because I've realised right from the beginning,
during these talks and dialogues,
that relationship is the greatest importance in life.
Right.
Without that, life is chaos.
Got it.
That has been driven into me.
Mm-hmm.
And I see every flattery and every insult is registered
in the brain.
Right.
And thought then takes it over,
memory,
and creates an image.
That's right.
And the image gets hurt.
When you say the image is the hurt...
Is the hurt.
Quite.
Because the image is the pleasure,
and then with the new content of insult,
when the content is flattery, the image is pleasure,
and when the content is insult, the image is hurt.
Right.
That's right.
So, Dr Bohm, what is one to do?
What am I to do?
How am I?
There are two things involved in it.
Yes.
One,
to prevent further hurts...
Mm-hmm.
Right.
And to be free of all the hurts that I've had.
But they're both the same principle, aren't they?
I think you explained to me.
I think there are two principles involved.
Are there?
You see, one to prevent it.
The other, to wipe away the hurts I have.
I don't know how to put it a little bit other way.
It's not just that you want to prevent the further hurt,
but it seems to me you might have
to be a little bit more careful.
I think you must first say,
how am I to be aware of the fact that I take flattery?
I mean, how are you going to get aware?
I want you to be...
Look, I want you to see that if I flatter you,
you get a big inner gush,
you start feeling big inside your belly,
and then you get a fantasy about,
well, if you were...
If you're wonderful this way,
then you'll be twice as wonderful.
So now you've got an image of yourself
as this wonderful person who fits this flattery.
I want you to see yourself eat my candy.
No, you have told me very clearly
it is the two sides of the same coin.
Pleasure and pain are the same.
The same, exactly the same.
Yes, you have told me that.
That's right. I'm telling you that.
I've understood it.
They are both images.
Both images.
Right.
So how am...
Please, my question you're not answering.
How am I realizing all this?
I'm a fairly intelligent man.
I've read a great deal.
Ordinary man.
I personally don't read,
so ordinary man I'm talking about.
Right.
I've read a great deal.
I've discussed this,
and I see how extraordinarily important all this is.
Right.
And I say,
I realized that the two sides of the same coin.
Right.
The brain registers and the whole thing begins.
Now how am I to end that?
Not the how, not the method.
Don't tell me what to do.
I won't accept it because it means nothing to me.
Right, sir?
Give me an answer.
Well, I mean we were discussing whether there is a difference
between the stored up hurts and the ones which are to come.
That's right.
That's the first thing I have to understand.
Tell me.
Well, I would...
It seems to me that, you know,
that fundamentally they also work on the same principle.
How?
Well, if you take the hurt that is to come,
and my brain is already disposed to...
you know, set up in order to make...
you know, to respond with an image.
No, I don't understand you.
Make it much simpler.
Well, it seems to me I'll make it.
I'm asking him.
You are an expert at it.
You have dozens of victims.
He has only one victim here.
Well, see, the...
there is no distinction really between the past hurts
and the present one because they all come from the past.
I mean, come from the reaction of the past.
So you are saying...
That's right.
You are telling me don't divide the past hurt or the future.
Yes.
Because the image is the same.
The process is the same.
Process...
Therefore the image is receiving.
Right?
Yes.
Yes, it really doesn't matter
because I may just be reminded of the past hurt.
That is the same as somebody else insulting me.
Yes.
Right?
So you are saying to me,
don't divide the past or the future hurt.
There is only hurt.
Yes.
There is only pleasure.
So look at that.
Look at the image,
not in terms of the past hurts and the future hurts,
but just look at that image which is both the past and the future.
Yes.
Right?
We are saying look at the image,
not in its particular content but its general structure.
Yes, that's right.
Now then my next question is,
how am I to look at it?
Because I have already an image
with which I am going to look.
That I must suppress it.
You promise to me by your words,
not promise exactly,
give me hope that if I have right relationship,
I live a life that will be extraordinarily beautiful,
I will know what love is and all the rest of it,
therefore I have already excited by this idea.
But then I have to be aware of the image of that kind too, right?
Yes, yes.
Therefore how am I – that's my point –
how am I to look at this image?
I know I have an image,
not only one image, but several images,
but the centre of that image is me, the I,
I know all that.
Now how am I to look at it?
May we proceed now?
Right.
Is the observer different from that which he is observing?
Yes, well...
That is the real question.
Yes, well, you could say that's the root
of the power of the image.
Yes.
You see, sir, what happens?
If there is a difference between the observer
and the observed, there is that interval of time
in which other activities go on.
Well, yes, in which the brain sort of eases itself
into something more pleasant, would you say?
Yes, yes.
But, yes, that's all right.
And where there is a division, there is conflict.
So you are telling me to observe in a different way,
learn the art of observing, which is that the observer
is the observed.
Yes, but I think we could look first at our whole tradition,
you see, our whole conditioning, which is the observer
is different from the observed.
Of course.
And perhaps we should look at that for a while.
Yes.
Because that is what everybody feels.
Yes, that the observer is different.
Yes, and I think it ties up with what I was saying yesterday
about reality.
Yes.
Saying there is a reality, everything we think is reality
of some kind, you see, because at least it's thought,
real thought.
But there is... we make a distinction in reality
between that reality which is self-referenced,
self-sustaining, you know, it stands independent of thought,
and the reality which is sustained by thought, right?
Yes, reality sustained by thought.
And the reality which may have been made by man,
but it stands by itself like the table, or else like nature,
which is different.
Yes, that we went through.
And now the observer...
ordinarily we think that when I am thinking of myself,
that self is a reality which is independent of thought.
Do you see?
Yes, we think that is independent of thought.
And that self is the observer who is a reality...
Quite.
...who is independent of thought and who is thinking,
who is producing thought.
But it is the product of thought.
Yes, but that is the computer.
Yes, quite, quite, quite.
Now...
Are you telling me, sir, as an outsider,
that the observer is the result
of the past?
Yes, one can see that...
My memories, my experiences, all the rest of the past.
Yes, but I think if we think of the viewer now,
he might find it a little hard to follow that,
if he hasn't gone into it, you see.
Very hard, I think.
How to communicate to...
Ah, wait, it is fairly simple.
What do you mean?
Don't you live in the past?
Right.
I think I exist in the past.
Wait a minute.
No, no, your life is the past.
Right.
You are living in the past.
Right?
That's right, yes.
Past memories, past experiences...
Past memories, past becoming, trying to...
And from the past you project the future.
That's right.
Hope will be better, I'll be good, I'll be different.
Right.
It's always from the past to the future.
That's right.
That's how it's lived.
Now, I want to see that past,
and past is the me.
Of course.
But it does look as if it's something independent...
just that you are looking at.
Is it independent?
It isn't, but to see that...
I know, that's what we are asking.
Is the me independent from the past?
It looks as if the me is here looking at the past.
Of course.
Quite.
The me is in a jar, in a can, and that's looking...
quite.
That's right.
But the me is the product of the past.
Right, you can see that.
But what is that jump that we go through...
where we say the me is...
I can say to you, I can see that I am the product of the past.
I can see that.
How do you see it?
Intellectually.
I see it intellectually.
Then you don't see it.
Right, that's what I'm coming to.
Then you are playing tricks.
Right.
I see it as an intellectual.
That's right, that's right.
I see it intellectually.
Do you see this intellectually?
No.
Why?
There's an immediacy of perception there.
In the same way, why isn't there an immediacy of perception...
of a truth which is that you are the past?
Not make it an intellectual affair.
Because time comes in.
I imagine that I've gone through time.
What do you mean, you imagine?
Well, I have an image of myself at three.
I have an image of myself at five.
I have an image of myself at ten.
And I have an image of myself at seventeen.
And I say that they followed in sequence in time.
And I see myself having developed over time.
I am different now than I was five years ago.
Are you?
Well, I'm telling you, that's how I've got that image.
That image is of a developmental sequence in time.
I understand all that, sir.
Right?
Yes.
And I exist as a storehouse of memories...
of a bunch of accumulated incidents.
That means time has produced that.
Right. That is time. I see that.
Time. What is time?
I just described it to you.
Time is a movement in a minute.
It's a movement.
That's right.
Right?
The movement from the past...
That's right.
That's it. I moved from the time of three...
From the past. It's a movement.
That's right. From three to ten, seventeen...
It's a movement.
Right.
Now, is that movement an actuality?
What do you mean by actuality? Or is it an image?
Is it an image or is it an actual fact?
That's it, yes.
I mean, you see, if I have an image of myself...
and saying, I need this...
but that may not be an actual fact.
Image is not a fact.
Right.
But I feel...
What you feel is like saying, my experience...
your experience may be the most absurd experience.
No, but that's casting me aside by saying...
look, you've got this going on...
I'm describing an actual...
But that's the whole point about the image...
is that it imitates an actual fact.
You've got that feeling it's real.
You see, in other words, I feel that I'm really there...
an actual fact looking at the past...
at how I developed.
But is that a fact that I'm doing that?
What do you mean?
It's an actual fact that I get the feeling that I'm looking there.
Yeah, but I mean, is it an actual fact that that is...
that that's the way it all is and was and so on?
Do you see that that is...
all the implications of that are correct?
No, it is not an actual...
I can see the incorrectness...
Uh-huh.
in my memory which constructs me in time.
I mean, obviously I was much more at three...
than I can remember.
I was much more at ten than I can remember.
And there was much more that went on, obviously...
an actuality at seventeen...
than I have in my memory.
Yeah, but now the me who is here now...
is looking at all that.
That's right.
But is he there and is he looking?
That's the question.
Is the me that is...
an actuality...
as this is?
Well, let's...
Stick to it, stick to it.
That's what I'm going to do.
What is an actuality is...
this image of a developmental sequence.
And the me who is looking at it.
And the me who is looking at it, right.
That's right.
You see, I think that's one of the things we slip out...
because we say there is the developmental sequence...
objectively.
So implying me is looking at it...
like I'm looking at the plant, right?
Right.
But it may be, or in fact it is...
that the me who is looking at it...
is an image as is the developmental sequence.
Right.
You're saying then that this image of me is...
Is non-reality.
It is no reality.
Well, the only reality is that it's thought, right?
Yes.
It is not a reality independent of thinking, right?
So we must go back to find out what is reality.
Right.
Reality, we said, is everything that thought has put together.
The table, wait a minute, the illusion...
the churches, the nations...
everything that thought has contrived, put together...
is reality.
But nature is not reality.
It's not put together by thought.
But it's a reality.
It's a reality independent of thought.
Independent of thought.
Right.
But you see, it is the me who is looking...
a reality that is independent of thought like nature.
That's the whole point.
You understood?
Yes, I'm beginning to see.
Let me ask you a question.
Can you say anything about the difference for you...
between your...
No, that's not fair.
I was going to say, is there any difference...
between this perception, the perception of this...
and your perception of the me?
This is real, me is not real.
Me is not real, but your perception of me.
It doesn't exist.
Suppose you perceive it.
But your perception of the image.
I have no image.
If I have no image, where is the me?
But I have an image of me.
Could I put it another way?
What's my perception of me?
Suppose you're watching a conjuring trick...
and you perceive a woman being sawed in half.
And then when you see the trick, you say...
what is your perception of this woman...
who is being sawed in half?
You say it isn't because she isn't being sawed in half.
I'm trying to say, as long as you don't see through the trick...
what you see, apparently real...
is somebody being cut in half.
But you've missed certain points.
But when you see the points that you've missed...
you don't see anybody being cut in half.
You just see a trick.
So I've missed the essence of it.
No, sir, let's be simple.
We said we have images.
And I know I have images...
and you tell me to look at it.
To be aware of it.
To perceive the image.
Is the perceiver different from the perceived?
That's all my question.
I know, I know.
Because if he is different...
then the whole process of conflict will go on endlessly.
But if there is no division...
the observer is the observed...
then the whole problem changes.
Right.
Right?
So is the observer different from the observed?
Obviously not.
So can I look at that image without the observer?
And is there an image when there is no observer?
I don't know.
Because the observer makes the image.
Because the observer is the movement of thought.
Well, we shouldn't call it the observer then...
because it's not looking.
You see, I think the language is confusing.
The language, yes.
Because if you say it's an observer...
that implies that something is looking.
Yes, quite right.
What you're really meaning is that...
thought is moving and creating an image...
as if it were looking, but nothing is being seen.
Therefore there is no observer.
Quite right.
But put it round the other way...
is there a thinking without thought?
What?
Is there a thinker without thought?
No.
Exactly. There you are.
If there is no experiencer...
is there an experience?
So, you've asked me to look at my image...
and you say, look at it...
which is a very serious...
and very penetrating demand.
You say, look at it without the observer.
Because the observer is the image-maker.
And if there is no observer...
if there is no thinker, there is no thought.
Right?
So, there is no image.
Right.
You have taught me...
you have shown me something enormously significant.
As you said, the question changes completely.
Completely. It's gone. I have no image.
It feels completely different.
It's like then there is a silence.
So, I'm saying, as my consciousness...
is the consciousness of the world...
because in essence...
it's filled with the things of thought...
sorrow, fear, pleasure, despair...
anxiety, attachment, detachment, hope...
all turmoil...
of confusion...
a sense of deep agony involved in it all.
And in that state...
you cannot have any relationship...
with any human being.
So, you say to me...
to have the greatest...
and the most responsible relationship...
is to have no image.
That's to be responsive to what is.
Don't translate it.
Well, it is.
It means to be responsive...
to open it up.
So, you have pointed out to me...
that to be free of images...
the maker of image must be absent.
The maker of the image is the past...
is the observer who says...
I like this, I don't like this...
it's my wife, my husband, my house...
you follow?
The me...
who is in essence the image.
So, you see, I've understood this.
Now, next question is...
is the image...
deep, hidden?
Are the images hidden...
which I can't grapple...
which I can't get hold of?
You follow, sir?
Are they in the car...
in the underground...
somewhere hidden...
which you have told me there are?
All you experts have told me...
yes, there are dozens of...
underground images.
How am I...
because I accept you...
I don't...
I say, yes, by Jove...
they must know...
they know much more than I do...
therefore, they say so...
so I accept it.
So I say, yes...
there are underground images.
Now, how am I to...
unearth them...
expose them out?
See, you have put me...
the ordinary man...
into a terrible position.
Well, you don't have to unearth them...
once this...
if this is clear to you...
there is no...
But you...
but you have established already in me...
the poison...
You don't exist anymore.
Once it's clear to you...
that the observer...
is the observed...
therefore, you are saying...
there is no unconscious.
Right.
You, the expert?
No, I said...
You, who talk endlessly about...
unconscious...
to your patients...
No, I don't...
No, I don't.
Therefore, you say...
there is no unconscious?
Right.
I agree with you.
I say, it is so.
Right.
The moment when you see...
the observer is the observed...
the observer is the maker of images...
Right.
it's finished.
Finished. Right.
Right through.
Right.
If you really see that...
That's it.
So, the consciousness...
which I...
in which...
which I know...
in which we have lived...
has gone a tremendous...
transformation.
Right.
Has it?
Has it to you?
No, sir.
I mean, don't...
Has it to you...
and if I may ask, Dr. Pong, both of us...
all of us...
realizing...
that the observer is the observed...
and therefore, the image maker...
is no longer in existence...
and so...
the content of consciousness...
which makes...
makes up consciousness...
is not as we know it.
Right?
What then?
You've got five minutes.
I don't know how to answer you there.
Sir, this is...
you follow?
Yeah.
I'm asking this question because...
it involves meditation.
I'm asking this question...
because all religious people...
the really serious ones...
I'm not talking the gurus and all their flummery...
the real serious people...
who have gone into this question...
as long as we live...
in daily life...
within the area of this consciousness...
of anxiety, fear, all the rest of it...
with all its images...
and the image maker...
whatever we do...
will still be...
in that area.
Right?
I may join one year...
Zen...
become a Zen, shave my head...
and do all kinds of stuff.
Then, in another year...
I go and become a...
some guru, follow guru...
and so on, so on...
but it's always within that area.
Right.
So...
what happens when I...
when there is no...
movement of thought...
which is the image making...
what then takes place?
You understand my question?
When time...
which is the movement of thought...
ends...
then what...
what is...
what is there?
Because you have led me up to...
up to this point.
I understand it very well.
I have tried Zen Buddhism...
I have tried Zen meditation...
I have tried Hindu meditation...
I have tried all the kinds of...
miserable practices and all that.
And I meet you...
I hear you...
and I say...
by Jove, there is something extraordinary...
these people are saying.
They said...
the moment there is...
when there is no...
image maker...
the content...
of consciousness...
undergoes...
a radical transformation...
and...
thought...
comes to an end...
except when it is absolutely...
has its right place...
knowledge and...
all the rest of it.
So thought comes to an end.
Time has a stop.
What then?
You understand?
Is that death?
It is the death of the self.
And that is the death...
of the self.
We have got...
three minutes more.
We have got one minute more.
One minute more.
Oh, it is destruction.
No, no, sir.
It is much more than that.
It is the end of something.
No, no.
Just listen to it.
When thought stops...
when there is no image maker...
there is a...
complete transformation...
in consciousness...
because there is no anxiety...
there is no fear...
there is no pursuit of pleasure...
there is none of the things...
that create turmoil...
division.
What...
comes into being...
or what happens...
not as an experience...
because that is out...
what takes place in there?
Because...
you follow?
I have to find out.
You may be leading me...
up the wrong path.
Right, we better stop.